<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The liberty of the subject by Magna Charta, or, Several weighty things to be considered of by the jurors and judges, seeing the law of England is said to be a law of mercy and doth take care jurors be of the next neighbourhood ...</title>
            <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40936</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F489</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14907</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13591418</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13591418</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100671</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40936)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100671)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 788:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The liberty of the subject by Magna Charta, or, Several weighty things to be considered of by the jurors and judges, seeing the law of England is said to be a law of mercy and doth take care jurors be of the next neighbourhood ...</title>
                  <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Richard Farnworth.  Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Magna Carta.</term>
               <term>Liberty --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100671:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100671:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Liberty of the Subject BY Magna Charta: OR, Several weighty things to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of by the Jurors and Judges, ſeeing the Law of <hi>ENGLAND</hi> is ſaid to be a Law of Mercy, and doth take care that Jurors be of the next Neighbourhood, moſt ſufficient Men, and Perſons that are leaſt ſuſpicious: And that Judges and Miniſters of Juſtice are to do even Law and Execution of Right to all Men, rich and poor, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of perſons.</p>
            <p>And, That <hi>MAGNA CHARTA,</hi> and the Charter of the Forreſt are to be allowed in all their points; and that if any Judgement be given contrary to the Points of the Charters by any of the Kings Miniſters of Juſtice, it is to be undone and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for naught. 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.2.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, No man is to be put to anſwer without preſentment before Juſtices, or matter of Record by due proceſs, or by Writ Original, according to the old Law of the Land, and if any thing be done to the contrary it ſhall be void in Law, and holden for errour. 42 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Written in the 6th. Month, 1664.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:100671:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100671:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:100671:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100671:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE Liberty of the Subject BY Magna Charta: OR, Several ſerious and weighty confide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, as hereafter followeth.</head>
            <argument>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Becauſe the Innocent ſhall not be worn and waſted by long Impriſonment.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> That Priſoners for criminal cauſes when they are brought to their Tryal be humanely dealt withal.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> The Judge ought to exhort him to anſwer without fear, and that Juſtice ſhall be duly adminiſtred unto him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>FOraſmuch as the Law of <hi>England</hi> is ſaid to be a Law of Mercy, and that three things are favoured in Law. 1. Life. 2dly. Liberty. And 3dly. Dowre. And That there are two things which the Law delights in. Firſt, To have things openly and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly done. Secondly, Certainty,<note place="margin">Cook <hi>2.</hi> part. Inſtitut. fol. <hi>315.316.</hi>
               </note> for Truth is ſaid to be the Mother of Juſtice, and Certainty the Mother of quietneſs and repoſe:<note place="margin">Cook <hi>1.</hi> part. Inſtitut. fol. <hi>224.39.</hi>
               </note> What care therefore ought the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and Judges to have in executing the late Act, made for preventing and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing ſeditious Conventicles, that they
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100671:4"/>may not do things uncertainly nor unjuſtly and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mercy, nor that they may not ſeek to ſuppreſs the Truth, and People of God, inſtead of ſuppreſſing Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and preventing Inſurrection; nor that they may not puniſh the Innocent inſtead of the Guilty. Ought they not in order to the Executing of the ſaid Act, to take theſe things hereafter following into due and ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That religious and godly Meetings which are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the Service and Worſhip of God, are neither ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted unlawful Aſſemblies, nor prohibited, or puniſhable by the ſaid Act. But ſeditious and ungodly Meetings are prohibited and puniſhable thereby. For it is ſedition and contriving Inſurrection at Meetings under colour of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Worſhip, that makes Meetings to be unlawful Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, and ſeditious Conventicles puniſhable by the ſaid Act, and not ſuch godly religious Meetings as are far off and free from Sedition in word or action, and alſo from deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or contriving any Inſurrection.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That ſuch Meetings upon the account of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Worſhip of God as are not contrary to the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner allowed by the Liturgy or practice of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are not prohibited, nor puniſhable by the ſaid Act, but ought to be freed from the force of the penalties in that caſe provided.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That for people to aſſemble and meet together without any intent either to ſowe Sedition, or to contrive Inſurrection, but onely to wait upon the Lord in the way of his Worſhip, and to preach and pray, and to perform duty and ſervice to God at any time, or in any place, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the gift and requirings or teachings of the Word and Spirit of God, is not contrary to what is allowed by the Liturgy of the Church, becauſe the Liturgy alloweth the ſame.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That for perſons and people to aſſemble and meet together under colour of religious Worſhip, with an
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100671:4"/>intent to contrive Inſurrection, is to meet in other manner then is allowed by the Liturgy or practiſe of the Church; becauſe neither the Liturgy nor practiſe of the Church al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth of any ſuch things.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Otherwiſe, ought not the Jurors and Judges to conſider whether according to Law, and in order to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain legal determination of the matter in a legal manner, it ought not firſt to be determined by the Spiritual Judges? <hi>viz.</hi> What Meetings upon the account of Religion and Worſhip of God are allowed by the Liturgy of the Church or contrary to the manner allowed by the Liturgy or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Church, before the Jurors or temporal Judges ought to finde a verdict, and paſſe Judgement accordingly to puniſh the perſons and people for ſuch matters and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſeeing it is a ſpiritual matter and cauſe, being about the Service and Worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Ought they not to conſider whether it belongs unto them to judge and condemn perſons for ſpiritual cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and matters of Conſcience in things appertaining to the Worſhip of God? or whether they ought not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim it as not belonging to their juriſdiction, becauſe they do not ſit and act as Judges in a ſpiritual capacity, but in a temporal; for is not the body politick divided into two parts, the one part called by the name of ſpirituality, and the other called the temporality; and are not their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers diſtinct, the one to hear and determine ſpiritual mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and cauſes, and the other to hear and determine temporal cauſes and matters: and hath not the body ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual power when any cauſe of the Law Divine happens to come in queſtion, or of ſpiritual learning, to declare and determine all ſuch doubts, and to adminiſter all ſuch offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and duties as to their room ſpiritual doth appertain? and are not the Laws Temporal for tryal of property of Lands and Goods, and for the conſervation of the people of this Realm in unity and peace without ravine or ſpoil by the Temporal Judges, and the other by the Spiritual
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100671:5"/>Judges?<note place="margin">24. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> or as by the Statute appeareth: ſee the Statute, 24. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Ought they not to conſider that people are not to be puniſhed (by the late Act) for the Service and Worſhip of God; but for meeting together to ſowe Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or to contrive Inſurrection under pretence of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Worſhip; and muſt it not be made apparent and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that they do ſo. <hi>viz.</hi> ſowe Sedition, or contrive Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, before they can or ought truly according to Law be found guilty, or condemned by the late Act ſo as to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the penalties thereof.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, ought not they to conſider, 1. Againſt what perſons and practiſes the remedies by the ſaid Act are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided. 2. Who they are that come within the reaſon of the Act. 3. For what end the penalties are to be executed. And 4. What Meetings are accounted and declared by the ſaid Act to be unlawful Aſſemblies, and puniſhable thereby, that thoſe may not be puniſhed but acquitted who are not guilty thereof?</p>
            <p>Ninthly, It is not evident, firſt that the Title of the Act is to prevent and ſuppreſs Seditious Conventicles (and not godly religious Meetings.) 2. That the remedies provided by the ſaid Act are againſt the growing and dangerous pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes of ſedition. Sectaries and diſloyal perſons, who do at their Meetings contrive Inſurrections, as late experience hath ſhewed; but neither former nor preſent experience hath ſhewed any ſuch things to be done or intended at the godly Meetings of the innocent people reproachfully cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Quakers, who are utterly and abſolutely againſt ſowing of Sedition, or contriving of any Inſurrection, and ought therefore to be cleared, and clearly acquitted from the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties of the Act in that caſe provided, as not being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that comes within the reaſon of the Act, againſt whom the remedies are provided as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, Doth, or may it not clearly appear, that for perſons to meet together (in greater or leſſer numbers) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100671:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>to ſerve and worſhip the Lord, is no offence againſt Law, nor puniſhable by the ſaid Act: but for perſons to pretend to meet together under colour of religious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and do not intend it, but makes a religious pretence a colour to cover and perſecute a wicked intention under, ſo as to ſowe ſedition, and to deſign or contrive inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on under ſo fair a pretence.</p>
            <p>Eleventhly, Ought not the Jurors to enquire of that, to finde out the certainty and truth of the matter in iſſue or queſtion, in order to judgement or final determinations, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether ſuch a thing can be found out upon enquiry, and ſo clearly and evidently appear that perſons are guilty of contriving Inſurrection at Meetings under ſo fair a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence as aforeſaid, that they may ſuffer according to their deſerts who do appear to be guilty thereof: but if no ſuch thing appear upon tryal, is it not the duty of Jurors and Judges to acquit them that are not guilty either of ſowing Sedition, or contriving Inſurrection at Meetings as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid? conſider well of it.</p>
            <p>Twelfthly, Ought not the Jurors to conſider what Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are accounted and declared (by the late Act) to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Aſſemblies and puniſhable thereby? and doth, or may it not appear that ſeditious and tumultuous Meetings are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted and declared by the Statute it ſelf to be unlawful Aſſemblies. 1. Becauſe the Title of the Act is to prevent and ſuppreſs ſeditious Conventicles. 2. Becauſe the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies provided by the ſaid Act are againſt the growing and dangerous practiſes of ſeditions Sectaries and diſloyal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who under pretence of tender Conſciences do at their Meetings contrive Inſurrections, as late experience hath ſhewed. And 3dly. Becauſe the execution of the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, or the Act it ſelf is for the preventing of the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs that may grow by ſuch ſeditious and tumultuous Meetings, or as by the Statute appeareth.</p>
            <p>Thirteenthly, Is it ſo, that ſeditious and tumultuous Meetings are declared by the ſaid Act to be unlawful Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100671:6"/>that are to be prevented or ſuppreſſed as aforeſaid, ought it not to be made clearly apparent and evident to the Jurors, That the godly and religious Meetings of an innocent people, reproachfully called Quakers, are ſeditious and tumultuous Meetings, or elſe how can the Jurors juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemn them as unlawful Meetings, or Aſſemblies, to ſuffer the penalties of the ſaid Act? ought they not rather in duty to God-ward, and in diſcharge of their Office to clear them in the face of the Countrey, and to free them from the force of the penalties; conſider well of it in the fear and wiſdom of God, unto whom all muſt give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, who hath puniſhments for the wicked, and rewards for the righteous.</p>
            <p>Fourteenthly, Ought not the Jurors further to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that for perſons ſimply to meet and aſſemble together with out any intent to break the Peace (in a ſeditious and tumultuous manner) or to do any unlawful act with force or violence, is not an unlawful Aſſembly; but for perſons to aſſemble and meet together with an intent to break the Peace (in a ſeditious and tumultuous manner) or to do ſome unlawful act with force or violence; is an unlawful Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly.</p>
            <p>An Aſſembly of an hundred perſons or more (yea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though they be in armour) yet if it be not in terrour or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright of the people, and were aſſembled without any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to break the peace, it is not prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by theſe Statutes,<note place="margin">1 <hi>M.</hi> 12. 1 <hi>El.</hi> 17.</note> nor unlawful ſaith <hi>Dalton</hi> in his Juſtice of Peace: See <hi>Dalton fol.</hi> 279. It ſeemeth (ſaith he) it can be no unlawful Aſſembly except there be an intent precedent to do ſome unlawful act, and with violence, or force: ſee <hi>Dalt. I. P. fol.</hi> 279.</p>
            <p>And their being together (when they are aſſembled) and their demeanour muſt be ſuch, as ſhall or may breed ſome apparent diſturbance of the Peace, either by threatning ſpeeches, turbulent geſture, ſhew of armour, or actual force
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100671:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>or violence, to the terrour and fearing of the peaceabler ſort of people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or elce it can be no riot, rout, or unlawful Aſſembly, ſaith <hi>Dalton</hi> in his Juſtice of peace: ſee <hi>Dalton fol.</hi> 281.</p>
            <p>If little private Aſſemblies be Conventicles, doth not the Act it ſelf allow of Conventicles, becauſe it allows of little private Meetings, to the number of four, beſides them of the houſhold: it ſeems it is not Chriſtian Meetings, but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Conventicles that are prohibited and puniſhable as aforeſaid. Ought not therefore the Jurors to enquire whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the perſons aſſembled did ſowe ſedition, diſcord, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, and ſtrife, did they ſpeak any ſeditious words, or uſe any threatning ſpeeches, ſhew of armour, or actual force or violence, to the terrour and fearing of the peaceabler ſort of people, or how can it appear, that they are guilty of ſeditious and tumultuous words and actions, (or of being at ſeditious and tumultuous Meeting.) and if no ſuch things appear and be evident, is it not the duty of the Jury to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit them from the force of the penalties, to all intents, conſtructions, and purpoſes?</p>
            <p>Ought not the Judges or Juſtices to conſider what they are commanded and ſworn to do, that they may perform their duty in reſpect of their Office, and not break their Oathes. Are not they commanded and ſworn to do even, or equal Law, and Execution of right to all men, rich and poor, without reſpect of perſons. 2dly. Are they not to allow the great Chartars of the Liberties of <hi>England</hi> in all their points. 3dly. Are they not to do Juſtice and Right to all men, freely, without ſale, fully without denyal, and ſpeedily without delay. 4thly. Are they not to do all men Juſtice and Right, according to Law, and the uſage of the Realm. 5thly. Is it not according to Law, and the uſage of the Realm to convict or try Fellons, Traytors, and the worſt of men by the verdict of a Jury of good men and true? And how can perſons properly (according to Law and the uſage of the Realm) be ſaid to be offenders for a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100671:7"/>third offence in one and the ſame cauſe, matter, and thing, if they were never convicted of, and tryed by, a Jury of good men and true, for the firſt and ſecond offence, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Law and the uſage of the Realm.</p>
            <p>It is enacted by <hi>Magna Charta</hi> (confirmed by 32 Acts of Parliament) that no Free-man ſhall be taken or impriſoned,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>9</hi> Hen. <hi>3.</hi> cap <hi>29.</hi> Cooks Proeme to the <hi>2</hi> part Inſtit.</note> or diſ-ſeized of his Free-hold, or Liberties, or free Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, or be outlawed or exiled, or in any wiſe deſtroyed, nor we will not paſs upon him, nor condemn him, but by lawful judgement of his equals, or by the Law of the Land, we ſhall ſell to no man, we ſhall deny or defer to no man either Juſtice or Right. <hi>Magna Charta. cap.</hi> 29.</p>
            <p>Firſt, No man is to be taken or impriſoned, but by the Law of the Land, that is, by the Common Law, Statute Law, or cuſtome of <hi>England.</hi> Secondly, No man ſhall be diſſeized, that is, put out of ſeizen, or diſpoſſeſſed of his Free-hold, that is, Lands, Livelihood, or of his Liberties, or free Cuſtomes; that is, of ſuch Franchiſes and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and free Cuſtoms as belong to him by his free Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, unleſs it be by the lawful judgement, that is, verdict of his equals (that is) men of his own condition, or by the Law of the Land, that is, to ſpeak once for all by due courſe and proceſs of the Law. Thirdly, No man ſhall be outlawed, made an <hi>Ex lex,</hi> put out out of the Law, that is, deprived of the benefit of the Law, unleſs he be outlawed according to the Law of the Land. Fourthly, No man ſhall be exiled or baniſhed out of his Countrey, unleſs he be exiled and baniſhed by the verdict of his equals, or according to the Law of the Land. Fifthly, No man ſhall be in any ſort deſtroyed except it be by the verpict of his equals, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of the Land. Sixthly, No man ſhall be condemned at the Kings Suit, either before the King in his Bench, where the Pleas are <hi>Coram Rege,</hi> nor before any other Commiſſioner or Judge whatſoever, but by the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100671:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>of his Peers, that is, equals, or according to the Law of the Land. Seventhly, We ſhall ſell to no man Juſtice and Right. Eighthly, We ſhall deny to no man Juſtice or Right. Ninthly, We ſhall defer to no man Juſtice or Right: ſee <hi>Cook</hi> upon the 29. chap of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> 2. pt. Inſtit. fol. 45.46, 47, 48, 49, 50.</p>
            <p>No man ſhall be in any ſort deſtroyed, unleſs it be by the verdict of his equals, or according to the Law of the Land. And no man ſhall be condemned at the Kings ſuit before the King in his Bench, nor before any other Commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or Judge whatſoever, but by the judgement of his Peers, that is equals, or according to the Law of the Land, ſaith <hi>Cook</hi> upon <hi>Magna Charta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Niſi per Legem terra</hi>] but by the Law of the Land; for the true ſenſe and expoſition of theſe words, ſee the Statute of 37. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. where the words,<note place="margin">37. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 18.</note> by the Law of the Land are rendered without due proceſs of Law, for there it is ſaid, though it be contained in the great Charter, That no Man be taken, impriſoned, or put out of his Free-hold without proceſs of Law, that is by Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Preſentment of good and lawful men,<note place="margin">25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> where ſuch deeds be done in due man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or by Writ Original of the common Law: ſee <hi>Cook</hi> upon <hi>Magna Charta, fol.</hi> 50.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item.</hi> Whereas it is contained in the great Charter of the Franchiſes of <hi>England,</hi> that none ſhall be impriſoned, or put out of his Free-hold, nor Franchiſe, nor free Cuſtoms, but by the Law of the Land, it is accorded, aſcented, and eſtabliſhed, that from henceforth none ſhall be taken by petition, or ſuggeſtion made to our Sovereign Lord the King, or to his Council, unleſs it be by Indictment or preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his good and lawful Neighbours where ſuch deeds be done, in due manner, or by proceſs made by Writ Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal at the common Law; nor that none be put out of his Franchiſes, nor of his Free-holds, unleſs he be duly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100671:8"/>brought in to anſwer, and fore-judged of the ſame by way of Law: And if any thing be done againſt the ſame, it ſhall be redreſſed and holden for none. ſee the Statute 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>cap</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>No man ſhall be taken and impriſoned without being brought in to anſwer by due proceſs of Law: for it is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by a Statute made in the eight and twentieth year of the reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, that no man of what ſtate and condition ſoever<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he be, ſhall be put out of his Lands or Tenements, nor taken nor impriſoned, nor diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herited without, being brought in to anſwer by due proceſs of Law:<note place="margin">28. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> ſee the Statute it ſelf, 28. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3</p>
            <p>And no man is to be put to anſwer without preſentment before Juſtices, or matter of Record by due proceſs of Law: for by a Statute made in the two and fortieth Year of the Reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third,<note place="margin">42 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3</note> it is aſſented and accorded for the good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernance of the Commons, that no man be put to anſwer without preſentment before Juſtices of Record by due pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, or by Writ Original according to the old Law of the Land: and if any thing be done from henceforth to the contrary, it ſhall be made void in Law, and holden for er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, as by the Statue appeareth 42 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Is it not contrary to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the Law of the Land, to take men and impriſon them, and paſs judgement upon them in any caſe without due and legal proceedings? And if they have due and legal proceedings, are they not to be indicted or preſented by good and lawful people of the ſame neighbourhood where the fact or offence is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in due manner as aforeſaid; or elſe by proceſſe made by Writ Original at the common Law: and if that be denyed, and men be condemned before they be impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, and without verdict of their equals, and without being duly brought in to anſwer, and tryed by the courſe of the Law, are they not deſtroyed contrary to Law? or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100671:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>ought not ſuch things to be redreſſed and holden for none, as are againſt <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the Law of the Land as aforeſaid. And if any man be impriſoned, and be not du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought in to anſwer according to Law as aforeſaid, ought not the proceedings againſt him to be void in Law and holden for errour.</p>
            <p>If men cannot legally according to Law, and the uſage of the Realm, be tryed as offenders for the third offence for one and the ſame cauſe, matter, and thing; if they were never legally convicted of, and tryed for a firſt and ſecond offence, according to the great Charters of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of <hi>England,</hi> or the former Statutes and Laws of the Land as aforeſaid; may not that offence whereof they are firſt convicted and tryed by due proceſs of Law, according to the former Statutes of the old Law of the Land, be in Law taken and deemed to be the firſt offence, and the other be void in Law, ſeeing the Law takes care and provides that all men ſhall have even Law and execution of right without reſpect of perſons; and if they have not, where is the fault in the Law, or in the executors thereof, who are commanded and ſworn to do even Law and Execution of Right to all men, rich and poor, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons,<note place="margin">20. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1</note> or ſhewing favour to one more then unto another? they are not to with-hold Law and Right from men (for differences in judgement in matters of Religion) but they are to let them have even Law and right as well as others: ſee <hi>Magna Charta, cap.</hi> 29. And ſee the Statute 20 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>ch.</hi> 1. and 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.4. and 5. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.9. and 28. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. and 42. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>The Law takes care and provides that Jurors be of the next neighbourhood, moſt ſufficient men, and perſons that are leſt ſuſpicious, as by the Statute appears, 28. <hi>Edward</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>And no man is prohibited, but allowed by the Law of the Land to have Counſel of Pleaders, of learned men in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100671:9"/>the Law (for his fee) or of his next friends: ſo that a man may plead for his friend: ſee the Statute 28 <hi>Edward</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>The Laws and Cuſtoms of <hi>England</hi> ſhall be pleaded, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and defended, anſwered, debated, and judged in the Engliſh tongue in all Courts within this Realme, and are onely to be entred and enrolled in Latine: ſee the Statute for that, 36. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 15.</p>
            <p>Is it not the duty of a Judge to diſcern what is juſt by the rule of the Law, and ſo to make the Law his rule, his line, his meaſure, his weight, his yard, and ballance, which is called right it ſelf and common Law, becauſe it judgeth common right by a right line, which is the judge of it ſelf, and its oblique, ſaith <hi>Cook</hi> in his ſecond part <hi>Inſtitut.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Are not the Judges to do juſtice and right according to the rule of the Law and Cuſtome of <hi>England, Cook</hi> 2. pt. Inſtit. fol. 56.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are not to ſell, deny, or delay Juſtice and Right, neither the end which is juſtice, nor the means whereby the end may be obtained, which is the Law, ſaith <hi>Cook</hi> in his 2. part Inſtit. fol. 56.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Court ought to be of councel with the Priſoner, to ſee that nothing be urged againſt him contrary to Law and Right, ſaith <hi>Cook</hi> 3. part Inſtit. fol 29.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Judge ought to exhort the Priſoner to anſwer without fear, and that Juſtice ſhall be duly adminiſtred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, ſaith <hi>Cook</hi> in his 2. part Inſtitutes, fol. 316.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Judges of the Court who ever, are to be of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel with the Priſoner, to give him Law and Juſtice <hi>ex oſſicio,</hi> ought to enquire whether he be the ſame perſon, and of all other pleas which he might have pleaded, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſaith <hi>Cook</hi> in his 2. part Inſtitut. fol. 178.</p>
            <p>Nay, ſaith he, any learned man that is in the Court may inform the Court for the benefit of the Priſoner, of any thing that may make the proceedings erroneous, <hi>Cook</hi> 3 part Inſtit. fol. 29.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:100671:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Alſo, ſaith he. It is lawful for any man that is in the Court to inform the Court, leſt the Court ſhould erre, and the Priſoner be unjuſtly proceeded with: ſee <hi>Cook</hi> 3. part Inſtit. fol. 137.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Judges and Miniſters of Juſtice are to allow the great Charters of the Liberties of <hi>England</hi> in all their points: for by a Statute made for the confirmation of the Charters 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. cap 1. It is enacted that all Majors Sheriffs, Juſtices,<note place="margin">25 <hi>Ed</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> and other Miniſters which have the Laws of the Land to guide them, ſhall allow the ſaid Charters pleaded before them in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in all points: ſee the Statute it ſelf 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. cap. 1.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The Judges and Miniſters of Juſtice are not to give Judgement againſt the great Charters; for whatſoever judgement is given againſt the Statute of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> or of the Charter of the Forreſt, is made void by the Statute 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. cap. 2. becauſe (ſaith <hi>Cook</hi>) the judgement is given againſt the Law; and the Statute it ſelf ſaith, If any Judgement be given from henceforth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the points of the Charters afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid,<note place="margin">Cook <hi>2</hi> part In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. fol. <hi>226, 227</hi>
               </note> by the Juſtices or by any other, our Miniſters that hold Plea before them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the points of the Charters, it ſhall be undone and holden for naught: Statute 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. cap. 2.</p>
            <p>And by a Statute made the 42d. year of the Reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, it is aſſented and accorded that the great Charter, and the Charter of the Forreſt be holden and kept in all points;<note place="margin">42 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> and if any Statute be made to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that ſhall be holden for none: ſee the Statute it ſelf, 42 <hi>Edward</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>The great Charters are to be read four times a Year in the Counties, and twice a Year in the Cathedrals, that the people may know they are confirmed, and are to be kept in all points:<note place="margin">25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1, 2, 3.</note> ſee the Statute 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. cap. 1.2, 3.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:100671:10"/>
And it is enacted by the Statute of the 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. cap. 4. that all Archbiſhops, and Biſhops ſhall pronounce the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of excommunication againſt all thoſe that by word, deed, or Council do contrary to the aforeſaid Charters, or that in any point do break or undo them, and that the ſaid curſes be twice a year denounced and publiſhed: ſee the Statute 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cap. 4.</p>
            <p>All men are enjoyned to uphold and maintain the great Charters: ſee the ſentence of the Clergy given againſt the breakers thereof: In the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas our Sovereign Lord the King, to the honour of God, and the Holy Church, and for the common profit of the Realm, hath granted for him and his heirs for ever, thoſe Articles above written, <hi>Robert</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> Primate of all <hi>England,</hi> admoniſhed all his Province once, twice, and thrice, becauſe ſhortneſs will not ſuffer ſo much delay as to give knowledge to all the people of <hi>England</hi> of theſe preſents in Writing: We therefore enjoyn all perſons of what State ſoever they be, that they and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them, as much as in them is, ſhall uphold and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain theſe Articles granted by our Sovereign Lord the King in all points, and all thoſe that in any point do reſiſt or break, or in any manner hereafter procure counſel, or any wiſe aſſent to reſiſt or break thoſe ordinances, or go about it by word or deed, openly or privily, by any manner of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or colour. We the aforeſaid Archbiſhop by our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in this Writing expreſſed, do Excommunicate and Accurſe, and from the Body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and from all the company of Heaven, and from all the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of holy Church do ſequeſter and exclude.</p>
            <p>And as concerning liberty of Conſcience about matters of Religion, The King hath been pleaſed to promiſe and declare a liberty to tender Conſciences, <hi>viz.</hi> That no man ſhall be diſquieted and called in queſtion for differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of opinion in matters of Religion, ſo long as they do
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100671:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>not diſturb the Peace of the Kingdom. Now foraſmuch as the innocent people called Quakers have never diſturbed the Peace of the Kingdom by deſigning or contriving any Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They never yet forfeited their intereſt in the Kings promiſes; and the Act entituled <hi>An Act to prevent and ſuppreſs ſeditious Conventicles,</hi> provides remedies againſt the growing and dangerous practices of Seditious Sectaries and diſloyal perſons, who under pretence of tender Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces do at their Meetings contrive Inſurrections, as late ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience hath ſhewed: ſo that the remedies are provided by the ſaid Act againſt the growing and dangerous practices of ſuch perſons as have forfeited their intereſt in the Kings pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes by diſturbing the Peace of the Kingdom in contriving Inſurrection, and not againſt the Innocent Meetings of the people of God, reproachfully called Quakers, or ſuch as never yet forfeited their liberty therein, becauſe neither for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer nor preſent experience hath ſhewed that they ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived any Inſurrection, who are utterly and abſolutely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt deſigning or contriving any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>Of the Aſſemblies and Congregations of the faithful St. <hi>Hillary</hi> againſt <hi>Auxentius,</hi> ſaith, I pray you, O ye Biſhops, which do think your ſelves to be ſo, what ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages have the Apoſtles uſed for to preach the Goſpel?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>Act.</hi> 16.</note> with what power were they aided for to preach Chriſt, and as if it were to change all Gentiles from Images to God? have they taken any dignity of the Pallace, in ſinging of Hymnes and Pſalms unto God in priſon, being in Irons and Chains, and afterward to be whipped and ſcourged. Did <hi>Paul</hi> aſſemble the Church of Chriſt by the Kings Edict, when he was as a ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle in the Theatre? they nouriſhing and keeping themſelves with their own handy labour, in aſſembling themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether within Chambers and ſecret places, and by the Streets and Villages, did environ and compaſs about almoſt all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100671:11"/>by land and by water, againſt the Decrees and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or the Senators and Edicts of the Kings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Apology againſt he Gentiles, chapter 29. ſaith, This Aſſembly of the Chriſtians ſhould be very unlawful, if it were like or equal unto the unlawfull things; it ſhould be worthily condemned, if it were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of as of a Faction or Sect: but whom have we endamaged or hurt by our aſſembling and meeting to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; we are the very ſame, as when we were all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed aſunder every one by himſelf, not hurting any man When wiſe men, and good and faithful people do aſſemble themſelves together, we muſt not call that a Faction or Sect, but rather a Court: and on the contrary, we muſt apply the name of Faction unto thoſe which hate good men, that cry againſt the blood of the innocent under colour of their unity, and for defence of their hatred: Foraſmuch as they do eſteem and judge that the Chriſtians are the cauſes of all loſſes and common miſhaps. If the River <hi>Tiber</hi> mounteth or ſwelleth above the walls, if the River <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>las</hi> do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend upon the fields, if the heaven do ſtand ſtill, if the earth tremble, if there be Famine or Peſtilence; by and by they cry after the Chriſtians for to caſt them into the Lions Den.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Apology againſt the Gentiles ſaith on the behalf of the Chriſtians, ſo may I ſay on the behalf of the people of God, reproachfully called Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers. This aſſembling of theirs ſhould be very unlawful if it were like or equal unto the unlawful things of Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or contriving Inſurrection; or if they did meet with any intent to do ſome unlawful act with force or violence, either againſt the peace, or perſons of another, in a ſeditious and tumultuous manner: But whom have the Quakers, ſo called, endamaged or hurt by their aſſembling and meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100671:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>together; they are the very ſame (when they are met) as when they were all diſperſed aſunder every one by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, not hurting any man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Enſebius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ceſaria</hi> in his Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, lib. 6. chap. 11. Alledging the Epiſtle of <hi>Alexander</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> againſt <hi>Demetrius,</hi> and rebuking him, thus ſaith, That which thou haſt added in thy Letters thou ſayeſt That it was never ſeen that the lay and ſecular people ſhould diſpute of the Faith in the preſence of the Biſhops: I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel what moved thee to affirm a lye ſo evident; inſomuch that as often as there is found any man that is ſufficient and apt for to give good counſel, and to inſtruct the people; the Biſhops have accuſtomed to deſire him to do it, as our Brother the Biſhop <hi>Neon</hi> did unto <hi>Evelpius</hi> in the City of <hi>Laranda,</hi> and the Biſhop <hi>Celſus</hi> unto <hi>Paulinus</hi> in the City of <hi>Icomum,</hi> and the Biſhop <hi>Atticus</hi> unto <hi>Theodoſius</hi> in the City <hi>Sin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as.</hi> And there is no doubt but the other Biſhops may do the like in their Dioceſſes when they finde any one which is a man for to profit the people.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> upon the firſt Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> Hom. 8. ſaith, I deſire moſt earneſtly and do pray, that ye be all in the order of Doctors, and not onely to be hearers of our words; but alſo that ye would report and declare unto others our doctrine, and that ye would correct thoſe that do erre or go aſtray, to the end they may return into the way of truth; as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Exhort one another, and edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie one another,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And a little after he ſaith, God would not that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſhould be onely content with himſelf, but that he do alſo edifie others, and not onely with Doctrine, but alſo with good life and converſation.</p>
            <p>And when he was come into the Temple, the chief Prieſts and the Elders of the people came upon him as he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100671:12"/>was teaching, and ſaid, By what authority doeſt thou theſe things, and who gave thee this authority.</p>
            <p>They declared (ſaith <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi>) That there was ſome which did give power unto men, be it corporal or ſpiritual, as if they had ſaid thus, thou art not engendered of the ſacerdotal family, the Senate hath not permitted thee to do this, <hi>Caeſar</hi> hath not given it thee: But if they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that all power is from God, they would never have asked who hath given thee this power, knowing that every good gift, and every perfect gift is from above, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth down from the Father of Lights;<note place="margin">39. <hi>Hom.</hi>
               </note> and that a man can receive nothing at all except it be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him from above: ſee <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> upon the 21. chap. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> 39. <hi>Hom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antoninus Pius</hi> was a great defender of the Chriſtians: for <hi>Speed</hi> in the Hiſtory of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> ſpeaking of the care that this Emperour generally had for the diſtreſſed and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted Chriſtians; in whoſe defence he wrote to his depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and publiſhed an Edict againſt their Accuſers: the effect whereof (ſaith he) from <hi>Euſebius</hi> is this.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="edict">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:100671:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An Edict of <hi>Antoninus</hi> for protection of the Chriſtians.</head>
            <p>THe Emperour <hi>Caeſar, Marcus, Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, Antoninus, Auguſtus, Armeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. Eccleſ. Hiſt. l. 4. c. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Pontifex, Maximus,</hi> fifteen times Tribune, thrice Conſul unto the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>Aſia</hi> ſendeth greeting: I doubt not but the gods themſelves have a care that wicked perſons ſhall be brought to light; for it much more doth appertain unto them then it doth unto you, to puniſh ſuch as refuſe to yield them wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: but this courſe which you take doth confirm them whom you perſecute in this their opinion of you, that you are impious men, and meer Atheiſts; whereby it cometh to paſs that they deſire in the quarrel of their God, rather to dye then to yield to the wills of ſuch as you are, and to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the form of Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the behalf of theſe men (<hi>viz.</hi> the Chriſtians that were baniſhed and perſecuted to death for the ſervice of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal God) many of the principal Preſidents have written before unto our Father of famous memory: to whom he anſwered, That they ſhould not be moleſted, unleſs they were proved to have practiced Treaſon againſt the Emperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al State: and touching the ſame matter, ſome, have given notice unto me, to whom I have anſwered with the like mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration as my Father did before: And by this our Edict do we ordain, That if any hereafter be found thus buſie in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſting theſe kinde of men without any their offence, We command that the hat is accuſed upon this point be abſolved, albeit he be proved to be ſuch a man as he is charged to be, that is, a Chriſtian: and he that is his accuſer ſhall ſuffer the ſame puniſhment which he ſought to procure upon the other.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:100671:13"/>
This Edict was promulged at <hi>Epheſus</hi> in the general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. So favourable was this good Emperour (ſaith he) to the true profeſſors, and (indeed) to all ſorts of men, having that Apothegm of <hi>Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cio Aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rcanus</hi> rife in his mouth, That he had rather ſave one Subjects life then kill a thouſand Enemies. <hi>Speeds</hi> Hiſtory, fol. 100.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100671:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
